Neufeld, Maurice Papers /3007
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Maurice Neufeld Papers
1903-1994
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Neufeld, Maurice
/3007
64 cubic feet
64 linear ft.
Papers (documents), correspondence, manuscripts (documents), notes, news clippings (information artifacts), memorandums, case files, bibliographies, examination (documents).
Literary manuscripts, correspondence, class materials, subject files, case files, bibliographies, news releases, and newspaper clippings covering Neufeld's career as labor historian, consultant, and arbitrator.
3440145
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, January 10, 2002
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, January 14, 2016
Biographical / Historical
Professor Maurice Frank Neufeld (October 27, 1910 -April 10, 2003) was an American academic, author, union organizer and Army officer. In 1945, he was one of the two founding faculty members of the School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University, appointed by its founding dean, Irving Ives.
Scope and Contents
Literary manuscripts, correspondence, class materials, subject files, case files, bibliographies, news releases, and newspaper clippings covering Neufeld's career as labor historian, consultant, and arbitrator.
Series I, Correspondence/Administrative files, spans the period 1947-1987 and includes correspondence, memos, committee notes, student examinations, term papers and other materials collected during Neufeld's long tenure as professor in the School of Industrial and Labor Relations, Cornell University. Among the most significant correspondents represented in this series are Val Lorwin and Philip Taft.
Series II, Xerox Corporation files, consists of materials relating to Neufeld's work as industrial relations advisor to the company, mostly in Rochester, N.Y. Subjects include contract negotiations, employee grievances, and discipline, and relations between the company and the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union (ACTWU), which represented the employees.
Series III, Italy files, contains materials relating to Italian politics, culture, history, government, economic conditions and industrial relations.
Series IV, Publications, contains primarily of research materials, notes, and correspondence related to, as well as manuscripts of, Neufeld's published articles and books. Among the significant topics in this series is Neufeld's plan to study grievance procedures in the Soviet Union.
Series V, Class materials, includes bibiliographies, reading lists, class handouts, and student papers. Series VI, Miscellaneous, includes clippings, notes, manuscripts, articles, reports, and histories covering a number of individuals and topics.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4176: Maurice Neufeld Additional Papers /3007 AV: Maurice Neufeld "Grass Roots Founders and Grass Root Prodders: The Sources of Venture and Renewal for Democratic Education" Speech Audio-Visual Materials /4131m: Maurice Neufeld Additional Papers 5777: Maurice Neufeld Documents and Clipping Files /4229: Maurice Neufeld Additional Files /4230: Maurice Neufeld Additional Files 5515 5885: New York Times Additional Clipping File
Arrangement
Series I. CORRESPONDENCE/ADMINISTRATIVE FILES
Series II. XEROX FILES
Series III. ITALY FILES
Series IV. ARTICLES AND BOOKS
Sub-Series A. Publications Sub-Series B. Misc. Writings
Series V. CLASS MATERIALS
Sub-Series A. Class Handouts Sub-Series B. Student Term Papers
Series VI. MISCELLANEOUS
Sub-Series A. Subject Files Sub-Series B. National Labor Relations Board Files Sub-Series C. Thomas W. Holland
Industrial relations -- New York (State); Industrial relations -- Study and teaching -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Industrial relations -- Italy; Industrial relations -- Soviet Union; Labor discipline -- New York (State); Aribtration, Industrial -- New York (State); Industrial arbitrators -- New York (State); Collective bargaining -- New York (State); Grievance procedures -- New York (State); Grievance procedures -- Soviet Union; Industrial arbitrators; College teachers.; Italy -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Italy -- Economic conditions -- 20th century; Italy -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Lorwin, Val R.(Val Rogin), 1907-; Neufeld, Maurice F.; Taft, Philip, 1902-1976.; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations --Faculty.; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations --Students.; Xerox Corporation --Management.; Xerox Corporation --Employees.
3440145
- Series I. CORRESPONDENCE/ADMINISTRATIVE FILES
  - Allaway, Richard (former Ph.D. student) - Correspondence, 1947-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    Scope and Contents
    Routine correspondence
  - Academic Freedom, 1949-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
    Corres re 1968 sit-in at Econ 103 lecture, memo from Dean Murphy to univ. faculty re seizure of The Trojan Horse, corres re 1949 decision of Faculty Committee on Scheduling of Public Events (MFN chairman) to deny Eugene Dennis permission to speak at Cornell, and "The Position of the University with Regard to Communism". Includes newspaper clippings and articles.
  - Administration - ILR, 1946-1951 (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
    "NYSSILR Manual of Administrative Practices and Procedures" [9/48], "General Organization of ILR", Admissions Policy [4/5/48], corres from MFN to Dean Martin P. Catherwood ("Doc") re 1947-48 budget (MFN wrote, "The miracle is the fact that we are actually here.") [6/12/47], 1947-48 Budget, Memo from Ives to faculty and staff re Ives taking temporary leave of absence, Profs. Emerson and Shank and MFN to be on Administration Committee and act in Ives' stead, and MFN named Secretary [9/16/46], Memo from MFN to Ives re Course Assignments and Office Procedures [6/19/461.
  - Administration - ILR, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 11-14)
    Statements and memos re building requirements and plans, policy statement re private consulting, statement re Administration of the School, program planning discussions for Collective Bargaining, Labor History and Administration faculty [10/5/54], "Grad Study in ILR: A Statement of Standards and Practices" [accepted on 9/16/53]
  - Administration - ILR, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 15-18)
    Statement re Administration of the School [9/57], report of the Advisory Committee on Personnel Policies re extension staff [12/16/57], memo to faculty re corres from MFN to Prof. Vernon Jensen re modifications in degree requirements [1/8/57], memos from C.A. Hanson to faculty re answers for accreditation report [12/14/56 & 11/9/56].
  - Administration - ILR, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
    Memo from Dean McConnell to faculty re Administrative Organization of the School [7/7/59], memo from Prof. Milton Konvitz to MFN re naming ILR building Ives Hall [5/15/583, corres from Provost Atwood to ILR faculty re Dean's selection committee which includes MFN [12/22/58]; MFN couldn't serve on committee [12/29/58].
  - Administration - ILR, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
    "NYSSILR Long-Range Planning Report" [1/60], minutes of Faculty Administrative Conferences, corres from Mcconnell to MFN re postponement of selection of chair of Collective Bargaining, Labor Law, and Labor Movements dept. [7/7/60], memo from McConnell to faculty re department organization, "NYSSILR Long-Range Program of the School".
  - Administration - ILR, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Memo from MFN to McConnell re dedication of Ives Hall and publication re origins of the school [12/22/60]0., memo from McConnell re promotion of Prof. Smith to Secretary and Prof. Campbell to Extension Director [10/18/60], minutes of Faculty Administrative Conference
  - Administration - ILR, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
    Memo from Milton Konvitz to McConnell and full professors re teaching and/or research [5/30/62], minutes of meetings of ILR Staff Personnel Policy Committee
  - Administration - ILR, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Routine correspondence and minutes.
  - Administration - ILR, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Memo from Committee on Long-Range Planning and Faculty Personnel Policies re Revised Statement of Faculty Personnel Policies [5/25/64].
  - Administration - ILR, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Memo from MFN to Vernon Jensen re approval of Vernon Jensen's appointment to Asst. Dean for General Administration [5/19/65], memo from Dean Moore to faculty and staff re Vernon Jensen's appointment [5/13/65].
  - Administration - ILR, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
    Memo from MFN to Prof. Landsberger re the reaction of other departments at Cornell to the ILR School [9/1/653, ILR Working Paper [8/65].
  - Administration - ILR, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 32-33)
  - Administration - ILR, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    NYSSILR "Campus Academic Plan and Campus Development Plans for 1968", memo from Moore to faculty re public employee relations [2/12/68].
  - Administration - ILR, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 35-37)
    Memo from Vernon Jensen to faculty re faculty observations on institutional problems facing them [7/8/69], minutes of Administrative Conferences re Resident Instruction and Student Relations, memo from Moore to MFN re agenda for 1/21/69 & 1/22/69 retreat (w/ many addenda) [1/16/69], "Proposal for the Division of the OB Department".
  - Administration - ILR, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Minutes of Administrative Conference on Resident Instruction and Student Relations [5/15/70].
  - Administration - ILR, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Memo from Risley to faculty and staff re interim administration [1/7/71], memo from Moore to faculty and staff re Moore's decision to accept an appointment with the National Industrial Conference Board [9/28/70].
  - Administration - ILR, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Memo from William B. Wolf to Dean McKersie re "The ILR School in 1977: A Scenario" [4/17/72], memo from MFN to Wolf re forecast of personnel needs in the next five years [2/22/72].
  - Administration - ILR, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Routine
  - Administration - ILR, 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Administration - ILR - CB, LL, LM, 1958-1980 (Box 1, Folder 43-47)
    Memo from Prof. Roger Keeran to MFN re whether to keep ILR 200 as a requirement [2/20/76], memo from MFN to dept. faculty re resolution offered by MFN to change name of dept. from CB, LL, and LM to CB, LL, and Labor History [1/11/74], minutes of dept. meetings re appointing retiring profs. [2/27/72 & 3/1/72], corres from Prof. Korman to Prof. McKelvey re retirement of Vernon Jensen, Milton Konvitz, and MFN [3/20/72], memo from MFN to Wolf re Forecast of Personnel Needs [2/2/72], corres from MFN to Moore re election of Vernon Jensen as chairman [4/16/69], corres from MFN to Moore re MFN's resignation as chairman [3/10/69], corres from Moore to MFN re congratulations on MFN's election as chair [9/20/65], memo from Risley to MFN re MFN's chairmanship of dept. [5/18/59], corres from Mcconnell ("Jack") to MFN re thanks for acting as chairman [9/22/60].
  - Administration - ILR - CB, LM, LM - Manning Tables, 1960-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Memo from MFN to Mcconnell re faculty requirements, by priority, in dept. [4/15/60].
  - Administration - ILR - CB, LL, LM - Meetings, 1959-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2-6)
    Routine correspondence and minutes
  - Administration - ILR - CB, LL, LM - Teaching Appointments, 1961-1980 (Box 2, Folder 7-11)
    Removed and restricted
  - Administration - ILR - CB, LL, LM Teaching Assignments, 1960-1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Course schedules, course descriptions, corres re course offerings, corres from MFN to Vernon Jensen re MFN's teaching and sabbatical schedule and comparative labor history research [4/6/61].
  - Administration - ILR - International and Comparative Labor Relations Systems, 1959-1976 (Box 2, Folder 13-16)
    Memo from John Windmuller to Moore re appointment of Galenson to three-year term as dept. chairman [5/20/69], memo from John Windmuller to dept. members re Profs. Aronson, Vernon Jensen and Milton Konvitz terminating their dept. membership [9/11/67], memo from John Windmuller to dept. members re request for profs. to reconsider their dept, membership [4/19/67], minutes of dept. meetings, "Major Field in International and Comparative Labor Relations: Some Considerations", memo from Morris re Cornell - Ford Foundation terminal budget [8/5/65], corres from MFN to John Windmuller re renaming courses in International and Comparative Labor Problems to International and Comparative Labor Relations [4/19/65], minutes of meeting of members of the graduate faculty in the field of ILR (international and comparative labor relations was established as a graduate field minor) [10/31/58], memo from John Windmuller to Moore re invitations to MFN and Landsberger and Morris to join dept. and decision to check to see if Vernon Jensen, McKelvey, Aronson, and Milton Konvitz are interested in joining [5/10/60], memo from John Windmuller to Risley re ad-hoc planning committee [3/13/59].
  - Administration - ILR - Labor Economics and Income Security, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Memos re staffing
  - Administration - ILR - Manpower Research, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    "Proposal for the Division of the Department of Organizational Behavior".
  - Administration - ILR - Organizational Behavior, 1960-1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Memo from MFN to Profs. Foltman, Rosen, Friedland, and Cheek re lack of knowledge about personnel management by ILR undergraduates [4/12/65].
  - Advisory Committee - Labor - ILR, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Committee membership list for 1971-72 and 1972-73, minutes of committee meeting [11/5/71].
  - Advisory Council - ILR, 1951-1976 (Box 2, Folder 21-25)
    Memos from MFN to McKersie re MFN's suggestions of candidates for council membership, minutes of meetings (MFN said that the founders of the school believed that the first two years should have a liberal arts orientation but the school is moving away from being a liberal arts college [10/7/71]), meeting agendas, schedules of meeting events (w/ addenda, including 1962-63 nd 1963-64 budgets), memo from Aronson to McKersie re Undergraduate Program Committee's opposition to the offering of a B.S. degree program in New York City [3/23/73], "Report and Recommendations of Subcommittee on a Junior Semester in New York", memo from Miller re a non-resident MILR program for manpower practitioners considered, "Purposes and Objectives of NYSSILR" (from 1957 Accreditation Report), "Report for Advisory Council" [4/27/51]. Includes newspaper clippings.
  - Agency for International Development (AID), 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Organizational charts. Corres from MFN to John Windmuller re the appointment of a Director of AID Labor Affairs Office [8/31/64], corres from Edward C. Sylvester, Jr., Deputy Administrator for Labor Dept's Bureau of International Affairs re Labor Dept's request for information for a survey on manpower and technical assistance programs in Latin America [9/9/63], "Report of the African Labor Task Force" [8/31/62], corres from Leona Baumgartner, Assistant Administrator for Human Resources and Social Development, to MFN re MFN's study of AID's manpower and labor programs [5/23/63].
  - AID - Labor Advisory Committee - Correspondence, Memos, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Corres from MFN to Kenneth J. Kelley, Director of AID Labor Service, re MFN's approval of Labor Advisory Committee becoming a committee for AID as a whole [2/14/64], memo from Kelley re summary of committee meeting with George Meany [10/31/63], memo from Kelley to committee members re MFN's study of AID's labor programs [7/23/63], committee meeting agendas, corres from MFN to Kelley re MFN's inability to attend 10/25-26/62 meeting [9/17/62], corres from Kelley to MFN re MFN's appointment to committee for one year [7/25/62], corres from Kelley re general information re committee [5/16/62], corres from MFN to Fowler Hamilton re MFN's acceptance of an invitation to become a committee member [4/28/62].
  - AID - Labor Advisory Committee - Minutes, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - AID - Labor Advisory Committee - Reports, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 29-31)
    Minutes of Labor Affairs Coordinating Committee meetings, AID reports, committee's "Statement on Clay Committee Report" [4/12/63], Memorandum Agreement between the Secretary of Labor and AID Administrator [11/26/62], "Section-by-Section Analysis of the Proposed Foreign Assistance Act of 1962".
  - AID - Travel, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Anniversary (25) Celebration - ILR - CB, LL, LM, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Corres between MFN and Aryeh Neier, exec. director of New York Civil Liberties Union, re Neier's dinner address at CB dept. conference
  - Anniversary (25) Celebration - ILR- General and Miscellaneous, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Includes articles and routine correspondence.
  - Anniversary (25) Celebration - ILR, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
    11/7/70 Dinner -1970. Program and menu (includes program and menu of 11/12/45 dedication ceremony), transcript, corres from Martin P. Catherwood to MFN re letters and telegrams received by Martin P. Catherwood at or around celebration (includes telegram from Gov. Rockefeller) [11/23/70], corres to MFN re thanks, congratulations, and regrets at absence re celebration, Jane Addams' Letters. Includes newspaper clippings
  - Anniversary (40) Celebration - ILR, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 37-40)
    Corres from Doherty to MFN re success of celebration and the stellar role played by MFN [5/8/86], invitation and program, schedule of events, memo from MFN to Doherty re school founders [12/20/85]. Includes articles, photographs, and video cassettes of The Early Years and an interview of MFN.
  - Calendars, 1951-1979 (Box 3)
    Daily calendars of MFN and Maxine Box Henry (MFN's secretary).
  - Applications - Faculty, 1946-1972 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    Routine correspondence. Removed and restricted
  - Bernstein, Irving - Correspondence, 1961-1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Corres re volume of selected works of Irving Bernstein edited by MFN, Philip Taft, and Jack Barbash.
  - Bernstein, Meyer (United Steelworkers of America, International Affairs Director) - Correspondence, 1948-1977 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
    Corres re United Steelworkers of America and post-war Germany (including corres and law re establishment of codetermination rights [4/16/51]). Includes newspaper clippings
  - Bologna Center - Johns Hopkins University, 1954-1973 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    Corres re MFN's 1956-57 sabbatical at The Bologna Center (MFN was Co-Director of the Labor Relations Seminar). Includes newspaper clippings and articles
  - Brody, David - Correspondence, 1964-1983 (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
  - Christie, Robert (former Ph. D. student) - Correspondence, 1950-1970 (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
    Routine correspondence. Includes newspaper clippings
  - Columbia University Seminar - Labor and Working Class History, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Committees - ILR, 1947-1973 (Box 4, Folder 7-10)
    Report of ad hoc committee on the Human Affairs Program (HAP) and memos and other critiques of HAP, routine documents re HAP, memo from Faculty Advisory Committee on Personnel Policies re proposal to amend the ILR statement on recommended personnel practice to allow term appointments at the associate or full professor level without having the adjectives "visiting" or "acting" in the title and term appointments for a period of three years or less [4/13/61], memo from Mcconnell to faculty re consideration of the report of the Committee on Extension Activities (Mcconnell wrote, "Decisions with respect to [the report's recommendations] will have an important bearing upon the future of the School.") (w/ addendum) [4/12/61], "Report of the Temporary Advisory Committee on Faculty Personnel Policies" [5/3/56], draft statement of faculty re maintaining institutional neutrality in labor dispute between Cornell and building service employees [1/11/51], "Preliminary Report of the Committee on Advisors to New Students" [12/12/47].
  - Committees - ILR - Academic Integrity, 1963-1971 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Committees - ILR - Academic Standards and Scholarships, 1946-1977 (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
    Committee reports, NYSSILR Admissions Policy
  - Committees - ILR - Associate Degree Program - I, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 14-17)
    Routine correspondence and reports
  - Committees - ILR - Associate Degree Program - II, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 18-22)
    Minutes of committee meeting (MFN is chairman, Dr. Sidney Peck, associate dean of Labor College was fired by Empire State College, and student morale is low) [12/19/72], memos and reports re Labor College (including "Educational Programs Offered by ILR School and Empire State College in New York City" (cont) [4/14/72]), "Grass-Roots Founders and Grass-Roots Prodders: The Sources of Venture and Renewal for Democratic Education" by MFN [2/4/72], course offerings, memo from MFN to Profs. Gruenfeld and Cook re Philip Taft's decision to teach labor history at the Labor College [12/15/71]. Includes newspaper clippings and articles.
  - Calendars, 1960-1976 (Box 4)
    Daily calendars of Joyce Wright Box (MFN's secretary).
  - Committees - ILR - Associate Degree Program - III, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 1-6)
    "Report by the Ad Hoc Committee on the Associate Degree Program ... to the ILR Faculty ..." [3/28/73], memo from MFN to committee members re agenda for 3/8/73 (w/ addenda, including "Status of the ILR Participation in the Labor College") [3/2/73], memo from McKersie re the relationship between the ILR School and SUNY schools re Labor Studies [3/6/73], memo from McKersie re the possibility to offering ILR courses on Long Island [2/27/73], memo from President Corson re meeting with Chancellor Boyer (Boyer unwilling to give the ILR School more responsibility for the Labor College) [2/13/73], "Interview with Harry Van Arsdale, Jr., Hotel Commodore, 1/26/73, on the Origins of the Labor College, Metropolitan New York Learning Center, Empire State College, SUNY", memo from James W. Hall, President of Empire State College, to McKersie re Labor College (Hall wrote, "I think the progress we have made over the past year has been nothing short of phenomenal." and "it is absolutely essential... that Empire State College continue to play a primary role in the overall management and development of the Labor College.") [1/12/73].
  - Committees - ILR - Associate Degree Program - IV, 1973-1978 (Box 5, Folder 7-11)
    Annual reports of the New York City ILR Credit and Certificate Program, "Report of the Planning Committee on Off-Campus Credit Courses" [3/22/76], "The Academic Bargain" by Charlotte Gold (a report on the evolution of the program), 1973-74 Budget. Includes newspaper clippings and articles
  - Committees - ILR - Building Name and Dedication, 1959-1963 (Box 5, Folder 12-15)
    Memo from J. Gormly Miller to Profs. Campbell, Ferguson, and MFN re proposed motion for faculty action to name ILR classroom and library building Irving M. Ives Hall [12/22/59], routine correspondence
  - Committees - ILR - Dean Selection, 1962-1971 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Routine correspondence.
  - Committees - ILR - Extension - I, 1961-1971 (Box 5, Folder 17-20)